Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.10
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Re-election Campaign for Governor, 1982; X.
  - Events, 8.
    - Governor Thornburgh Committee (GTC) Campaign Events
      - 1984 General Election: Voting and Interviews, Harrisburg and Dauphin, November 6, 1984 (Box 149, Folder 64)
      - 1985 General Election: Voting, Harrisburg, November 5, 1985 (Box 149, Folder 65)
  - Press Files, 9.
    These materials relate to media items and are in nine sections, as follows: Announcements; Correspondence; Endorsements; Allen Ertel; Issues and Controversies; Media; Voter Groups; Governor Thornburgh Committee News Releases; and News Clippings. The materials include, for example: letters, campaign endorsements, campaign contributions, television spots, transcripts, news releases and newspaper clippings. The files are an interesting mix of both important campaign issues and also the inevitable controversies.
    - Announcement
      - Formal announcement of candidacy for reelection for Governor, March 2-3, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 1)
      - Biography of Dick Thornburgh, March 2, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 2)
      - Campaign Announcement Q & A's, Pittsburgh, PA, March 2, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 3)
      - News Stations Transcripts regarding Campaign Announcement, Hershey, PA, March 2, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 4)
      - KYW Transcript regarding Campaign Announcement, March 2, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 5)
      - Campaign Announcement Q & A's, Johnstown, PA, March 3, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence
      - Sample letters requesting contributions, 1979-1982 (Box 150, Folder 7)
      - Letters from Martha Bell Schoeninger, Republican State Committee Chairman, March-June, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 8)
      - Letters to the editors regarding errors in newspaper articles, August-October, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 9)
      - Letters to and from Paul Critchlow, Campaign Press Officer, February, 1982-January, 1983 (Box 150, Folder 10)
    - Endorsements
      - Press Conference with Philadelphia Labor Leaders regarding endorsement of Thornburgh, February 25, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 11)
      - Letters and news releases announcing endorsements of Thornburgh, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 12)
      - Material regarding U.S. Secretary of State Kissinger and Presidents Ford and Reagan endorsing Thornburgh, February-September, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 13)
      - Newspaper clippings regarding endorsements of Thornburgh, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 14)
    - Allen Ertel (D), Candidate for Governor
      - Ertel's news releases and correspondence, February-October, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 15)
      - Appearances: press conferences, speeches, and TV spots, June-October, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 16)
      - Endorsements, March-July, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 17)
      - Thornburgh's Press Office research regarding Ertel's record, March-October, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 18)
      - Newspaper clippings on Ertel, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 19)
    - Issues and Controversies
      - Thornburgh's Positions on Issues, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 20)
      - Bond Counsel Correspondence and Clippings, July, 1981 (Box 150, Folder 21)
      - Campaign expenses, 1981-1982 (Box 150, Folder 22)
      - Economic development newsletters, 1979-1982 (Box 150, Folder 23)
      - Governor's first administration news releases regarding economic development, 1979-1981 (Box 150, Folder 24)
      - Economic development memos, correspondence, and reports, 1980-1982 (Box 150, Folder 25)
      - Economic development news clippings, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 26)
      - Foreign travel, 1980-1981 (Box 150, Folder 27)
      - Gag Order, 1979-1981 (Box 150, Folder 28)
      - Gay Pride, 1979 (Box 150, Folder 29)
      - Ging Controversy, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 30)
      - Graterford Prison, 1981 (Box 150, Folder 31)
      - Frank Hoffman Taping, 1982 (Box 150, Folder 32)
      - Manderino, PA Representative James, 1979-1982 (Box 150, Folder 33)
      - Pennsylvania State Education Association (PSEA) memos and news releases, 1980-1982 (Box 151, Folder 1)
      - PSEA news clippings, 1981-1982 (Box 151, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence with PSEA, March-August, 1982 (Box 151, Folder 3)
      - PSEA lawsuit, 1982 (Box 151, Folder 4)
      - Personal finances disclosure, 1982 (Box 151, Folder 5)
      - Public Relations Empire, 1981-1982 (Box 151, Folder 6)
      - Rendell (Philadelphia's D.A.) Investigation, 1982 (Box 151, Folder 7)
      - Salaries, 1980 (Box 151, Folder 8)
      - Milton Shapp, former Governor, 1982 (Box 151, Folder 9)
      - Three Mile Island (TMI), 1979-1982 (Box 151, Folder 10)
      - Thornburgh Scranton Feud, 1982 (Box 151, Folder 11)
      - Wives and girlfriends patronage, 1979 (Box 151, Folder 12)
      - Women, Infants and Children (WIC) Program, 1981-1982 (Box 151, Folder 13)
    - Media
      - Thornburgh's Accomplishments, 1982 (Box 151, Folder 14)
      - Questions and Answers, April-September, 1982 (Box 151, Folder 15)
      - Correspondence regarding Debates, 1982 (Box 151, Folder 16)
      - Newspaper clips and press conference regarding debates, 1982 (Box 151, Folder 17)
      - Public Relations and Advertising Consultant Agreement, 1982 (Box 151, Folder 18)
      - Campaign Brochure Material, 1982 (Box 151, Folder 19)
      - Radio Campaign Ads, 1982 (Box 151, Folder 20)
        - Budget and Taxes, 1982; 1.
        - Human Services, 1982; 2.
      - Television Campaign Ads, 1982 (Box 151, Folder 21)
        - "Agriculture", 1982; 1.
        - "Before/After", 1982; 2.
        - "Budget/Taxes", 1982; 3.
        - "Consumers", 1982; 4.
        - "Corruption", 1982; 5.
        - "Crime", 1982
        - "Education", 1982; 6.
        - "Endorsements I, II, and III", 1982; 7.
        - "Graterford", 1982; 8.
        - "Human Services", 1982; 9.
        - "Jobs", 1982; 10.
        - "The Order", 1982; 11.
        - "Promises", 1982; 12.
        - "Record", 1982; 13.
        - "Reforming Welfare", 1982; 14.
        - "Seniors", 1982; 15.
        - "Southwest Jobs", 1982; 16.
        - "Southwest Roads", 1982; 17.
        - "Special Kids", 1982; 18.
        - "Taxes", 1982; 19.
        - "Three Mile Island (TMI)", 1982; 20.
        - "Tributes", 1982; 21.
        - "Vocational Training", 1982; 22.
      - Surrogate Speech Kits, 1982 (Box 151, Folder 22)
      - Press Kits, 1982 (Box 151, Folder 23)
      - Governor's Press Kit, 1982 (Box 151, Folder 24)
      - Inaugural Press Kit, January 17-18, 1983 (Box 151, Folder 25)
    - Voter Groups
      - Voter Group Campaign Report, 1982 (Box 152, Folder 1)
      - Blacks for Thornburgh, 1982 (Box 152, Folder 2)
      - Concerned Business People for Thornburgh, 1982 (Box 152, Folder 3)
      - Democrats for Thornburgh, 1982 (Box 152, Folder 4)
      - Educators for Thornburgh, 1982 (Box 152, Folder 5)
      - Farmers for Thornburgh, 1982 (Box 152, Folder 6)
      - Labor Leaders for Thornburgh, 1982 (Box 152, Folder 7)
      - Small Business for Thornburgh, 1982 (Box 152, Folder 8)
    - Governor Thornburgh Committee News Releases
      - February, 1982 (Box 152, Folder 9)
        - Governor Thornburgh Committee announced that they filed reports reflecting contributions of more than $840,000, February 1, 1982; 1.
        - The Governor Thornburgh Committee will hold major fund-raising dinner featuring U.S. Transportation Secretary Drew Lewis, February 11, 1982; 2.
        - Former President Gerald F. Ford will be featured speaker at March 23 fund-raising dinner in Pittsburgh, February 22, 1982; 3.
        - Telegram from Vic Raia requesting meeting to urge Thornburgh to seek election to a second term as Governor, February 23, 1982; 4.
        - Thornburgh receives endorsement from Nate Smith, community leader and long-time civil rights activist in Pittsburgh, February 25, 1982; 5.
        - Four major southeastern PA labor leaders, representing more than 90,000 union members, endorsed Thornburgh for a second term, February 25, 1982; 6.
        - A number of veterans' leaders from across the state have endorsed Thornburgh for a second term, offering their personal support, February 26, 1982; 7.
      - March, 1982 (Box 152, Folder 10)
        - Thornburgh begins two-day swing across Pennsylvania to announce plans regarding 1982 gubernatorial race, March 1, 1982; 1.
        - Thornburgh formally announced candidacy for reelection, March 2, 1982; 2.
        - Republican State Committee Chairman Martha Bell Schoeninger filed nomination petitions containing nearly 20\,000 names from all of PA's 67 counties on behalf of Thornburgh's reelection campaign, March 9, 1982; 3.
        - Thornburgh announced that Montgomery County Republican Chairman Robert B. Asher will serve as Campaign Director of reelection effort, March 11, 1982; 4.
        - Governor's report to the Firemen's Legislative Federation of Pennsylvania, March 27, 1982; 5.
      - April-May, 1982 (Box 152, Folder 11)
        - Letter to Congressman Ertel in response to his letter of March 31 regarding published accounts on alleged threat by Education Secretary Scanlon, April 1, 1982; 1.
        - Governor Thornburgh Committee announced that they filed reports reflecting contributions of more than $1,134,339 for period ending March 29, April 7, 1982; 2.
        - Thornburgh's bid for reelection was endorsed by the 800-member Local 2274 of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, April 28, 1982; 3.
      - June-July, 1982 (Box 152, Folder 12)
        - Governor Thornburgh Committee announced that they filed reports reflecting contributions of more than $1,882,193 for period ending June 7, June 16, 1982; 1.
        - Statement in response to claims by Democratic gubernatorial candidate Allen Ertel that a member of Asher's staff improperly recorded statements by Ertel at a recent public meeting, July 26, 1982; 2.
        - Further response to claims by Ertel that member of Asher's staff, Frank Hoffman, improperly recorded and took notes of statements by Ertel at public meeting, July 27, 1982; 3.
        - Labor Leaders representing thousands of members of southwestern PA unions, including the Teamsters, Boilermakers, Carpenters, Printing Trades, General Laborers and Painters, today endorsed Thornburgh for reelection, July 29, 1982; 4.
      - August-September, 1982 (Box 152, Folder 13)
        - Statement in response to claims by Democrat gubernatorial candidate Allen Ertel concerning utility rates in PA, August 3, 1982; 1.
        - Statement concerning Aug. 26 letter from Philadelphia District Attorney Rendell to Democrat gubernatorial candidate Allen Ertel with his response to allegations made by Ertel about letters sent by supporters of governor's reelection effort, September 1, 1982; 2.
        - Pittsburgh Federation of Teachers President Albert Fondy expressed his personal support of Thornburgh for Reelection, September 6, 1982; 3.
        - Thornburgh will be featured guest on WITF-TV's "Newsmaker" program, September 10, 1982; 4.
        - Leaders of three major statewide volunteer fire service organizations announced their endorsement of Thornburgh and Scranton for reelection, September 11, 1982; 5.
        - Thornburgh praised for his unprecedented disclosure of his personal income tax returns for himself and his family and called upon the governor's opponent to do the same, September 13, 1982; 6.
        - The reelection of Thornburgh and Scranton received the unanimous endorsement of the executive committee of the "Family of Leaders", September 16, 1982; 7.
        - Governor Thornburgh Committee called on Democrat gubernatorial candidate Allen Ertel to release his federal income tax returns for the past five years, as Ertel's official spokesman told the press he would, September 20, 1982; 8.
        - Governor Thornburgh Committee announced that they filed reports reflecting contributions of more than $2,526,776 for period ending September 13, September 21, 1982; 9.
        - Former Secretary of State Dr. Henry A. Kissinger called Thornburgh "one of the most distinguished public servants in our nation", September 24, 1982; 10.
        - Letter from Frank Ursomarso, lead representative for Governor Thornburgh Committee in debate negotiations with the League of Women Voters, to League President, Cornelia Toole, September 30, 1982; 11.
        - Thornburgh renewed the call for his opponent to make public his and his family's federal income tax returns for at least the past five years, September 30, 1982; 12.
      - October, 1982 (Box 152, Folder 14)
        - Letter to Ertel regarding disclosure of federal income tax returns, October 7, 1982; 1.
        - Governor Thornburgh Committee condemned the tactics practiced by the PSEA leadership clique on behalf of their gubernatorial candidate, Allen Ertel, October 7, 1982; 2.
        - Letter to Ertel regarding his increasing reliance on ex-Governor Milton Shapp as a major spokesman, October 8, 1982; 3.
        - Governor Thornburgh Committee released campaign's most current public opinion poll results on upcoming gubernatorial election, October 11, 1982; 4.
        - Letter to Ertel regarding his endorsement by public employee unions, October 14, 1982; 5.
        - Nearly two dozen prominent PA athletes and sports leaders announced their support of Thornburgh's reelection, October 14, 1982; 6.
        - Letter to Philadelphia Mayor William J. Green regarding October 14 Mailgram requesting a debate with Allen Ertel, October 18, 1982; 7.
        - Harrisburg Patriot News endorsed Thornburgh's reelection effort, October 18, 1982; 8.
        - Thornburgh's reelection bid received more endorsements from news organizations around the state, October 19, 1982; 9.
        - Governor Thornburgh Committee filed reports reflecting contributions and receipts totaling $3,209,322 for period ending October 18, October 22, 1982; 10.
        - Former State Secretary of Highways Bartlett rebuts misrepresentations and distortions about achievements of Thornburgh's administration, October 27, 1982; 11.
        - Eleven more newspapers joined growing list of PA news organizations to endorse Thornburgh's reelection, October 27, 1982; 12.
        - PA Federation of Teachers President Albert Fondy rebuts misrepresentations and distortions about achievements of Thornburgh's administration, October 28, 1982; 13.
        - Rev. Leon Sullivan of Philadelphia, nationally respected civil rights leader, formally endorsed Thornburgh for reelection and urged black citizens to vote for him, October 28, 1982; 14.
        - Rev. Jesse Jackson endorsed PA Governor Thornburgh for reelection, undated; 15.
    - News Clippings
      - General Campaign Clips, February-September, 1982 (Box 152, Folder 15)
      - Positive news stories, 1980-1982 (Box 152, Folder 16)
  - News Clippings, 10.
    There are numerous newspaper clippings from the 1982 campaign in two sections. The first section contains daily and weekly clippings generated by the campaign. The date range is April through November 1982. The second section contains news clippings, arranged by month, from the Governor's Office. The date range is November 1981 through January 1983. The combination of these two groups of news clippings completely documents the progress of the campaign.
    - Campaign clippings
      - April-November, 1982 (Box 153, Folder 1-21)
    - Governor's office clippings
      - November-December, 1981 (Box 154, Folder 1-2)
      - 1982 (Box 154, Folder 3-14)
      - January, 1983 (Box 154, Folder 15)
  - Post Election and Inaugural, 11.
    These materials begin with "Election Results," always important for a campaign. The next section, entitled "Post Election," includes news releases, cabinet changes, notes and memoranda. Thirdly is "Correspondence," an array of letters, cards, mailgrams and notes from a variety of people, organizations, VIPs, and foreign dignitaries. Lastly, there are files relating to the Inaugural, for example: newspaper articles, press kit, and Ginny Thornburgh's inaugural file.
    - Election Results/Election Night
      - Pennsylvania Election Calendar, December 1, 1978 (Box 155, Folder 1)
      - Governor Thornburgh Primary Petitions, February 24, 1982 (Box 155, Folder 2)
      - Primary Ballot Position, May, 1982 (Box 155, Folder 3)
      - Absentee Ballot Request, May, 1982 (Box 155, Folder 4)
      - Election Results including chart of results in 10 largest states, November, 1978 (Box 155, Folder 5)
      - 1982 Primary Election Results, July 9, 1982 (Box 155, Folder 6)
      - 1982 General Election Results and transcripts, November, 1982 (Box 155, Folder 7)
      - Thornburgh - Tax Returns - copies, 1982 (Box 155, Folder 8)
      - Legislations' Election Results, November, 1982 (Box 155, Folder 9)
      - Memo re election night, October, 1982 (Box 155, Folder 10)
    - Post Election
      - Congratulatory Telephone Calls, October 28, 1982 (Box 155, Folder 11)
      - Gifts and Flowers, November, 1982 (Box 155, Folder 12)
      - Routing Notes, November 11-December 17, 1982 (Box 155, Folder 13)
      - Governor Thornburgh Volunteer Thank You Notes, December 12, 1982 -January 11, 1983 (Box 155, Folder 14)
      - Department of State Post Election Notice, November 11, 1982 (Box 155, Folder 15)
      - ABKR (Alan B.K. Rabinowitz) Congratulatory Letter Memo, December 1, 1982 (Box 155, Folder 16)
      - Second Term Cabinet notes and press release, January 1983 (Box 155, Folder 17)
    - Inaugural
      - Inaugural miscellaneous, January 18-20, 1983 (Box 155, Folder 36)
      - Ephemera, 1983 (Box 155, Folder 37)
      - Inaugural news clippings, January, 1983 (Box 155, Folder 38)
      - Inaugural press kit, January 17-18, 1983 (Box 155, Folder 39)
      - Inaugural binder, January 17-18, 1983 (Box 155, Folder 40-41)
      - Ginny Thornburgh's Inaugural file, January, 1983 (Box 155, Folder 42)
  - Market Opinion Research (MOR), 12.
    These files were used and maintained by campaign staff and include data up to January 1984. At the time of the reelection campaign in 1982 national issues and economic discontent were negatively affecting state elections. Perceptions of the Governor's achievements were seriously affected, accounting for these careful polls during the reelection period and continuing for a year thereafter. At this time, too, Thornburgh's national electoral potential was being discussed and polls such as these were instructive.
    - Analysis and statistical summary, May, 1982 (Box 156, Folder 1)
    - Statistical Summary, June, 1982 (Box 156, Folder 2)
    - Survey and voting intentions, August, 1982 (Box 156, Folder 3)
    - Issues and perceptions, August, 1982 (Box 156, Folder 4)
    - Background information, August, 1982 (Box 156, Folder 5)
    - Summary tables and data, September, 1982 (Box 156, Folder 6)
    - Data, October, 1982 (Box 156, Folder 7)
    - Study data, analysis and National GOP report, November, 1982 (Box 156, Folder 8)
    - Analysis, December, 1982 (Box 156, Folder 9)
    - Overview, January-May, 1983 (Box 156, Folder 10)